ILGWU Chorus Records and Sheet Music 5780/214
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
ILGWU Chorus Records and Sheet Music
1991-1996
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE)
International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union (ILGWU)
Dodds, Malcolm
Tyler, Gus
5780/214
1 cubic feet
1 linear ft.
Records (documents).
The collection predominantly consists of sheet music arranged by song, also included are song books, chorus packets, and information about performances.
7249372
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, April 15, 2011
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, April 16, 2019
Biographical / Historical
The International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union was once one of the largest labor unions in the United States founded in 1900 by local union delegates representing about 2,000 members in cities in the northeastern United States. It was one of the first U.S. Unions to have a membership consisting of mostly females, and it played a key role in the labor history of the 1920s and 1930s. The union is generally referred to as the "ILGWU" or the "ILG". The ILGWU grew in geographical scope, membership size, and political influence to become one of the most powerful forces in American organized labor by mid-century. Representing workers in the women's garment industry, the ILGWU worked to improve working and living conditions of its members through collective bargaining agreements, training programs, health care facilities, cooperative housing, educational opportunities, and other efforts. The ILGWU merged with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union in 1995 to form the Union of Needle trades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE). UNITE merged with the Hotel Employees and Restaurant Employees Union (HERE) in 2004 to create a new union known as UNITE HERE. The two unions that formed UNITE in 1995 represented only 250,000 workers between them, down from the ILGWU's peak membership of 450,000 in 1969.
Biographical / Historical
The ILGWU Chorus was an organization within the ILGWU that brought together union members to perform songs for television and radio, and at conventions and other public events. Under the direction of Malcolm Dodds, the ILGWU Chorus was probably most-widely known for its performances of "Look for the Union Label" on television commercials in the mid-1970s. The song, written by Paula Green and composed by Malcolm Dodds, was part of the ILGWU's general campaign to educate the public about the union label, the work of the ILGWU, and the importance of both to consumers and workers alike. The ILGWU Chorus appeared at ILGWU conventions, AFL-CIO conventions, community and political events, and the group sang songs in Chinese, English, French, and Spanish.
Local unions, district councils, and regional departments also organized choruses, and in many instances, these groups pre-dated the ILGWU Chorus that gained national recognition in the 1970s. These smaller groups performed at local and regional meetings, community events, and sometimes at the ILGWU's international conventions. The musical revue, "My Name Is Mary Brown," for example, was performed by the Northeast Department at the ILGWU's Golden Jubilee Convention in 1950. Along with orchestras, theater groups, sports teams, and others, these choruses were one part of the union's active educational departments.
Scope and Contents
The records of the ILGWU Chorus consist primarily of sheet music, and minimal records relating to the chorus including attendance lists and administrative aspects of the group's performances. The photographs of the ILGWU Chorus include images from the group, as well as portraits of the chorus director Malcolm Dodds.
The ILGWU Chorus records and photographs at the Kheel Center document a very small fraction of the work of the group, thus researchers would do well to review other parts of the ILGWU Records for further documentation. Researchers should consider review the Report and Record of Proceedings of the ILGWU's conventions after 1975. These records of proceedings provide some general information about the work of the organization, and when they chorus performed, they list the songs performed. Also of interest are recordings of Union Label commercials in the ILGWU Audio-Visual Collection (5780 AV). These include several of the different commercials that were televised as part of the Union Label Campaign.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5780: ILGWU records 5780/214 P: ILGWU Chorus Photographs
Textile workers--Labor unions--New York (State); Clothing workers--Labor unions--New York (State); Dodds, Malcolm; Tyler, Gus; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union; Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Operations Department; Union of Needletrades, Industrial, and Textile Employees; UNITE HERE (Organization)
7249372
- The ACTWU Song Book (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Alegria (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Alle, Alle, Alleluia (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Allelujah (Box 1, Folder 4)
- All Day, All Night (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Alas! And Did My Savior Bleed (Box 1, Folder 6)
- All Angels Songs (Box 1, Folder 7)
- A Mother's Prayer (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Amazing Grace (Box 1, Folder 9)
- America, The Beautiful (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Angels We Have Heard on High (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Angel of Freedom (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Blessed Assurance (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Bless Ye the Lord (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Bread of Life (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Cairo Mio Ben: Thou, All My Bliss (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Celebration (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Christmas Music (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Come, Ye Disconsolate (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Do You Hear What I Hear (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Emmanuel, Emmanuel (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Eres Tu; Touch the Wind (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Good Old American Love (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Family (The American Family) (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Feliz Navidad (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Freedom (Mandella) (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Go Tell It on the Mountains (Box 1, Folder 27)
- God Bless America (Box 1, Folder 28)
- God Bless America (Medley) (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Good-Time (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Great Day! Great day! (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Great Is Thy Faithfulness (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Happy Days Are Here Again (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Hark! The Herald Angels Sing (Box 1, Folder 34)
- He's Got the Whole World in His Hands (Box 1, Folder 35)
- I Am on the Battlefield for My Lord (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Granada (Box 1, Folder 37)
- I Cannot Tell It All (Box 1, Folder 38)
- I Couldn't Hear Nobody Pray (Box 1, Folder 39)
- I Hate Winter (Box 1, Folder 40)
- I Surrender All (Box 1, Folder 41)
- I Have Decided to Follow Jesus (Box 1, Folder 42)
- I Want Jesus to Walk With Me (Box 1, Folder 43)
- I Think I Heard Him Say (Box 1, Folder 44)
- It's Great to Live in America (Box 1, Folder 45)
- I Wanna, Wanna, Wanna, Wanna (Box 1, Folder 46)
- If I Can Help Somebody (Box 1, Folder 47)
- ILGWU Merry Christmas (Box 1, Folder 48)
- I Love to Tell the Story (Box 1, Folder 49)
- It Came Upon A Midnight Clear (Box 1, Folder 50)
- It is Well with my Soul (Box 1, Folder 51)
- Jesus Is All the World to Me (Box 1, Folder 52)
- We Are Climbing Jacob's Ladder (Box 1, Folder 53)
- Jay's Day (Box 1, Folder 54)
- Joy to the World (Box 1, Folder 55)
- Jesus, Jesus, Jesus in the Morning (Box 1, Folder 56)
- Jesus is the Rock That Lasts (Box 1, Folder 57)
- Jesu Tawa Pano (Box 1, Folder 58)
- Jesus, The Light of the World (Box 1, Folder 59)
- Joe Hill (Box 1, Folder 60)
- Joy to the World (Box 1, Folder 61)
- Just a Closer Walk with Thee (Box 1, Folder 62)
- Key Bread (Box 1, Folder 63)
- Let It Breathe on Me (Box 1, Folder 64)
- Let Us Break Bread Together (Box 1, Folder 65)
- Lift Every Voice and Sing (Box 1, Folder 66)
- Look Away; Kum Ba Yah (Box 1, Folder 67)
- Life Is Just a Bowl Full of Cherries Together (Box 1, Folder 68)
- Lord, I Lift Your Name on High (Box 1, Folder 69)
- Look for the Union Label (Box 1, Folder 70)
- Look for the Union Label (Chinese) (Box 1, Folder 71)
- Look for the Union Label (English, Spanish, French) (Box 1, Folder 72)
- Lord, I'm Coming Home (Box 1, Folder 73)
- Make Us One (Box 1, Folder 74)
- Memory (Box 1, Folder 75)
- Miracles from Heroes (Box 1, Folder 76)
- Mondale (Battle Hymn of the Republic) (Box 1, Folder 77)
- Michael, Ran the Boat Ashore (Box 1, Folder 78)
- If I Can Help Somebody (Box 1, Folder 79)
- E Pluribus Unum (Box 1, Folder 80)
- My May (Box 1, Folder 81)
- Nana de Belen (Box 1, Folder 82)
- New Lady of Liberty (Box 1, Folder 83)
- New York, New York (Box 1, Folder 84)
- Night of Silence (Box 1, Folder 85)
- Oh Freedom (Box 1, Folder 86)
- Oh Little Town of Bethlehem (Box 1, Folder 87)
- Oh Come, All Ye Faithful (Box 1, Folder 88)
- O God, Our Help In Ages Past (Box 1, Folder 89)
- O Music (Box 1, Folder 90)
- On the Move (Box 1, Folder 91)
- Over My Head (Box 1, Folder 92)
- Peace like a River, Kum Ba Yah (Box 1, Folder 93)
- Rangel (Box 1, Folder 94)
- Rejoice, Rejoice (Box 1, Folder 95)
- Roll the Imports Back (Box 1, Folder 96)
- Roll the Union On (Box 1, Folder 97)
- Unite Rhythm Exercises #1 (Box 1, Folder 98)
- Right Hand, Left Hand (Box 1, Folder 99)
- Basic Pulses (Box 1, Folder 100)
- Rhythm 1 (Box 1, Folder 101)
- Rhythm 2 (Box 1, Folder 102)
- Rhythm 3 (Box 1, Folder 103)
- Rubye's Music (Box 1, Folder 104)
- Save the New York Daily News (Box 1, Folder 105)
- Seek Ye First (Box 1, Folder 106)
- Shalom Havereen; Dona Nobis Pacem; Havah Nagilam (Box 1, Folder 107)
- Shine on me (Box 1, Folder 108)
- Solidarity Forever (Box 1, Folder 109)
- Someone to Watch Over Me (Box 1, Folder 110)
- Silent Night (Box 1, Folder 111)
- Sing Legato (Box 1, Folder 112)
- Songs (Box 1, Folder 113)
- Soon-a Will Be Done (Box 1, Folder 114)
- Soon and Very Soon (Box 1, Folder 115)
- Stand With Us, America; Havah Nagilah; We are the Girls (Box 1, Folder 116)
- Standing on the Promises (Box 1, Folder 117)
- Steal Away to Jesus (Box 1, Folder 118)
- Swing Low, Sweet Chariot (Box 1, Folder 119)
- That's Entertainment (Box 1, Folder 120)
- Tasty Fruit Cake (Box 1, Folder 121)
- The "Chaikin Rap" (Box 1, Folder 122)
- The Star-Spangled Banner (Box 1, Folder 123)
- The Unclouded Day (Box 1, Folder 124)
- The Triangle Shirtwaist Fire (Box 1, Folder 125)
- Together (Box 1, Folder 126)
- There Is a Balm in Gilead (Box 1, Folder 127)
- The First Noel (Box 1, Folder 128)
- U.N.I.T.E. (Box 1, Folder 129)
- U.N.I.T.E. (Chords) (Box 1, Folder 130)
- U.N.I.T.E. HERE (Box 1, Folder 131)
- Union Label (Box 1, Folder 132)
- Union Made (Box 1, Folder 133)
- UNITE Chorus Music Exercises (Box 1, Folder 134)
- UNITE Solfege (Box 1, Folder 135)
- UNITE Vocal Exercises 1 (Box 1, Folder 136)
- Up Where We Belong (Box 1, Folder 137)
- Victory Is Mine (Box 1, Folder 138)
- Vocalizes (Box 1, Folder 139)
- Walter Mondale Song (Box 1, Folder 140)
- We Shall Not Be Moved (Box 1, Folder 141)
- We Shall Overcome (Box 1, Folder 142)
- We Shall Override (Box 1, Folder 143)
- We're for Bill (Box 1, Folder 144)
- We're for Clinton (Box 1, Folder 145)
- We're for Dinkins (Box 1, Folder 146)
- We're for Hilary (Box 1, Folder 147)
- We're Marching to Zion (Box 1, Folder 148)
- We're Proud to be the Union (Box 1, Folder 149)
- CORO Songs (Box 1, Folder 150)
- We're UNITE (Box 1, Folder 151)
- What a Friend We have in Jesus (Box 1, Folder 152)
- What Child Is This (Box 1, Folder 153)
- Where Do You Stand (Box 1, Folder 154)
- When We UNITE (Box 1, Folder 155)
- Which Side Are You On? (Box 1, Folder 156)
- With Union Solidarity;(And other songs) (Box 1, Folder 157)
- Women Light the Way for Change (Box 1, Folder 158)
- Solidarity Day, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 159)
  Scope and Contents
  8/31
- Union Label; Other Songs (Box 1, Folder 160)
- Chorus (Box 1, Folder 161)
- A Tribute to Sol Hoffman (Box 1, Folder 162)
- Local 23-25 News, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 163)
  January
- UNITE Chorus (Box 1, Folder 164)
- Labor Day Parade, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 165)
- Chorus; Convention, 1994-1995 (Box 1, Folder 166)
- Various Songs (Box 1, Folder 167)
- Choral Series Songs (Box 1, Folder 168)
- The LIGWU Song Book (Box 1, Folder 169)
- Chorus - R. Jones Info (Box 1, Folder 170)
- Malcolm Dodds (Box 1, Folder 171)
- Chorus - Grand Central, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 172)
- Triangle Fire, 1992-1996 (Box 1, Folder 173)
- R. Jones Local 23-25 Chorus (Box 1, Folder 174)
- Terry Johnson Poem (Box 1, Folder 175)
  mounted on cardboard